and I want to tell you the story today
that's at the foundation of Western
civilization or one of the stories that
the foundation of Western civilization
because I think the Egyptian story
qualifies and I think the Mesopotamian
story qualifies and so this is the
judeo-christian Genesis story which I
think is as it's a staggering story if
you look at the structure of the Old
Testament what what happens first near
the first is that there's there's two
things that constitute what I think are
a radical split between different forms
of time and so one of them is Noah's
Flood where all the chaos comes washing
back and the world is remade so there's
that like the time before the flood now
in more traditional Christian societies
so say a hundred and fifty years ago
that was definitely considered a special
kind of time before the flood compared
after the flood and I think that the Old
Testament is set up that way there's
also the Tower of Babel so this story of
the Tower of Babel where people build a
tower that's going to reach to heaven
and God basically stops them by making
it unable to communicate with each other
and then they dispersed around the world
that's also a kind of chaos story so
there's the Tower of Babel and the story
of Noah and then after that then there's
the story of Abraham and what happens is
that the stories in the Old Testament
start to become quasi historical you
know they're like they're like tribal
history in a sense like they're
mythologized tribal history so they're
more than just tribal history but but
before that I think what they are is
they're almost there almost pure
archetype and we have no idea how old
the stories are so we know that the
story of creation in Genesis at the at
the beginning of Genesis there's
actually two creation stories there and
they're timelines don't exactly match up
and the hypothesis basically is is that
one tribal group or or group of tribes
had
one creation story and another tribal
group or group of tribes had another
tribal creation story and they came
together and they didn't really know how
to sort out their damn creation stories
because they both held them as sacred
and so what seemed to have happened over
time was that those stories were told
and then when they were written down an
editor they called the redactor tried to
sequence them so they made some sort of
sense and a lot of a lot of the Bible is
actually the attempt to take diverse
archaic archetypal and quasi historical
stories and to organize them in a
narrative manner while simultaneously
minimizing the internal contradictions
and it's a very very difficult thing to
do and it's not like only one person did
it thousands of people have participated
in doing it over huge stretches of time
so the historical element of the Bible
is probably roughly in the same of the
same age as the Mesopotamian stories so
you know you can stretch written history
back about 5,000 years something like
that maybe a little bit farther than
that so that's all we're talking about
with regards to written history and you
know people think of 5000 years ago as a
long time but it's not a long time you
know that's only 50 100 year old men so
it's a very interesting way to think
about it you know that's that's not a
very long long period of time the
stories before the flood I think they're
there in determinately ancient I think
they have their roots in like very very
early shamanic practices and they're
associated with ways of thinking that
have characterized people ever since
they became people everything since they
became whatever we are there have been
human beings like us anatomically
speaking for about a hundred and fifty
thousand years and we're also a little
bit Neanderthal about five percent two
to five percent something like that so
but are anatomically similar ancestors
being around for about 150,000 years
looks like we discovered fire about two
million years ago so and we've been
cooking for two million years
so anyways it kind of gives you a bit of
a time frame now the first part of the
there's basically in the Genesis story
there's a story about the creation of
being and then there's two stories
actually and then there's a story about
the creation of human beings and so the
first part of this story I'm doing I'm
gonna read this to you because I can't
it's too complicated for me to just spin
out spontaneously there are two
structural elements described in the
first chapter in Genesis chaos that's
one and heavens and the earth okay so
there's two structural elements one
process creation and one actor God or
the Word of God who's engaged in the
process the first structural element
chaos is signified by a word called this
is a Hebrew word tail and that means
chaos by Tohu for waste or for matter
without substance and by the bohu for
emptiness or confusion so the chaos out
of which God extracts order has those
elements it's chaos waste matter without
substance and emptiness and confusion so
the interesting there's a psychological
element there too right so I would say
in in some sense it's equivalent to the
chaos that you fall into when everything
falls apart around you and that's
associated with the shamanic idea that
during the shamanic transformation the
shaman goes back to the beginning of
time roughly speaking into the chaos
that precedes the emergence of order and
that's part of the shamanic
transformation ritual so the chaos that
the chaos that's conceptualized as the
ground of being is is partly the
potential out of which matter arises but
it's also partly the state of confusion
that you're in when everything when
order falls apart around you and that
makes sense if you think about it
because
the order that's being described in
Genesis is the order that makes up being
and so it makes sense when the order
that makes up your being collapses that
you're going to fall into something
that's equivalent to the original chaos
it's a very interesting way of thinking
about it I don't think it's metaphorical
by the way it's not metaphorical it's a
different way of describing reality so
it's like not like a metaphor for matter
it's different than that it's it's an
analysis of the structural components of
being and basically what you have is
chaos order and the thing that mediates
between them and we've talked about that
already as being the fundamental
tripartite constituents of reality
itself there has to be potential there
has to be something to interpret the
potential and then there has to be
something to mediate between the two
things so these three words Tejon Tohu
and bohu are very interesting for a
variety of reasons and profitably bear
further investigation the canadian rabbi
itzhak marmar stein who has begun to
explain the torah one word at a time
describes tale by the way tale and
timeout are the same word okay so that's
worth knowing and that's I got that from
Northrop Frye so the tale is a is like
the first syllable of the word timeout
and so we know that the mesopotamian
crew some people think the Mesopotamian
creation story preceded the creation
story that's in the judeo-christian
account but no one really knows there
was like a slew of creation stories with
roughly similar sub structures in the
Middle East at that time and the
Mesopotamian stories a manifestation of
it so does the judeo-christian story and
they their temporal order I don't think
is actually even calculable because I
think they both disappear into
prehistory fundamentally so but it's
very interesting to know that the tale
Miz associated with the idea of time map
because it also gives you some idea of
the because you don't know what the hell
ancient Hebrew words mean right well how
do you know that you're not there
anymore and so it's interesting to see
the association Network so you can
understand the concepts and so whatever
the tale ms which is this pre-existent
chaos is sort of like Tiamat who's the
terrible thing that raises up her head
when chaos is coming back it's also the
thing that that Marduk has to confront
with his eyes open and that Marduk
figure is very much like the Word of God
in the judeo-christian story because the
Word of God is the thing that's like
it's exploratory and communicative and
it's the thing that right that raises
order out of chaos so I don't think that
you can understand that without
understanding or I think that
understanding the Mesopotamian story and
the role of Marduk in relationship to
time outs sheds a substantial amount of
light on the relationship between the
Word of God and the initial chaos
they're parallel ideas so one of the
things that I should tell you about
Christianity which is which is
incomprehensible to me I don't
understand it is that so one of the
representations of the Word of God that
extracts order out of chaos is logos and
that's partly the root word of logic but
it's a lot more than that logos
basically means something like it means
something like heroic confrontation with
the unknown and the communication of the
results thereof it's it means roughly
that and one of the things that the
Christians did was assimilate Christ to
the logos that existed at the beginning
of time it's a very very strange idea
and it's a kind of mystical or artistic
insight that's difficult to - it's
difficult to understand how that idea
couldn't even happen and so so in some
sense what the Christians did with the
idea of logos by associating that with
Christ was to make Christ who's a
redeemer figure into the same thing that
generated order out of chaos at the
beginning of time and so that part kind
of puts them in the same conceptual
class as Horus and in the same
conceptual class as Marduk and I'll tell
you later that it also puts them in the
same conceptual class as Buddha but I'll
get to that story later so so also what
that means is that there's an idea that
that lurks latent lis in Christianity
that the ideal person is a and that's
partly the person who accepts the
necessity of death
and rebirth as part of the redemptive
process is identical to the thing that
at the beginning of time called order
out of chaos it's a phenomenal
conception and one of the things that
I've tried to argue in a paper that no
one's ever read is that the reason that
Western culture is predicated on the
idea that human beings have an
unalterable divinity which is basically
the source of their natural rights is
because it's predicated on the idea that
the individual consciousness partakes of
the process that's capable of pulling
order out of chaos or capable of
mediating between the two and that
there's something that's literally
divine about that and one of the things
that i also promote in this paper is
that you all believe that because you
act on it like you accept the idea that
that there are natural rights and that
people have individual rights and that
they have intrinsic value you don't know
why and you don't know what that idea is
predicated on from a metaphysical
perspective but you do accept it and you
do act it out and so to me what that
means is you believe it whether you know
it or not now you can argue about that
because you could argue about what it
means to believe something but I tend to
think that belief exists in relationship
to action rather than into what in
relationship to objective
conceptualization and so the idea and
then there's a very interesting little
twist in the Genesis story because what
happens when God makes man and woman and
this is a very bizarre thing is that he
basically says that men and women are
made in the image of God now God in that
particular story is plural but that's
not really relevant to our to our
concerns and I think that's remarkable
in a variety of ways because number one
well we don't exactly know what the
image of God means but we can place that
in relationship to the idea that it was
the Word of God that that extracted
order out of chaos and so what that
seems to intimate is that it's the
capacity of the human being to extract
order from chaos that's equivalent to
divinity perhaps in a reduced form and I
think that that's a I think we believe
that I think that we believe that and I
think it's right
even worse than that and then the other
thing that so damn bizarre about that is
it's not just men it's women too and
that's something that's something that I
have a very difficult time accounting
for because I don't understand why a
society that was as deeply patriarchal
as say the H Jewish Society why in the
world that that would also be attributed
to women but it is anyway so it doesn't
matter so there you know that the the
the identity with God is equally
distributed between men and women so
that's quite cool so anyways back to
Rabbi it's Jack marmar Stein
he describes tale as the unfathomable
undifferentiated womb out of which
existence as we experience it emerges
all potential exists in this primordial
energy or state so it's potential so in
some sense that's what the chaos is
potential and so I've been thinking
about that for a long time too because
it seems to me that what people actually
interact with is potential you know we
think we interact with matter but I
don't think we do I think we interact
with all the various possibilities that
matter might manifest and that's not the
same thing so that when you're
interfacing with your existence what
you're doing is taking a very large
number of potential futures which are
basically laid out in front of you and
actualizing one or the other as a matter
of your choice and so I think the thing
you're interacting with isn't matter
it's the multiple potential states that
matter could manifest itself in and I
think that's what we call potential and
consciousness seems to collapse that
into an action into into actuality so
all potential exists in this primordial
energy or state metaphorically it is a
confused seething mass the abyss the
deep and the surging bellowing of the
waves Tohu similarly is a chaotic
condition so that's interesting because
there's a psychological element there or
a place without color or form or more
specifically
something that seems to for a moment to
have form but when looked at again loses
that form toh who is the subjective
effect of chaos the force that confounds
people and that causes them to have
misleading visions so it's very
psychological in nature that that
particular concept and then verbo who
finally is related to toh who I'm sure
I'm pronouncing those wrong but means
more specifically the indistinct
entangled confused mass that all forms
once were prior to their division into
separate kinds of objects
so the heavens and the earth so those
are the next elements so apart from the
chaos comprise the vast and spiritually
stunning places that rise above us as
well as the material domain that makes
up our physical being and the physical
being of those things we experience this
material domain is both a trap in which
our consciousnesses are caught and the a
priori precondition for individual
existence in its destructive and
vulnerable but potentially redemptive
aspects the creation narrative in
Genesis has deeply embedded within it
the idea that the materiality of the
world clothes partial beings incomplete
avatars of God whose purpose is the
continuation and potential perfection of
the incompletely manifest being
characterizing the original creation
this process so that's that's the
process now we've got the order and
we've got the chaos and now we've got
the process the process creation is
characterized by the second word in
Genesis which is bara according to the
Kabbalist Ayden Stein sells the creation
represented by bara is not the coming
into existence of something new but the
transmutation of a divine and
illimitable reality in some into
something defined and delimited
particularized and actualized this
analysis of bara seems very illuminating
first because it attributes genuinely
creative power to consciousness and
cognition creative the limiting and
second because it seems so closely
related to the Christian idea of the
logos logos one of the most remarkable
of all the ancient philosophical or
theological conceptions is a word with
an extraordinarily broad range of
meaning it means our everything our
modern word consciousness means and more
it means mind and the creative actions
of mind exploration discovery
reconceptualization reason and speech
logos is further something whose
relationship to the mirror material is
so fundamental that the material does
not really exist at all in its absence
finally it is something whose workings
are essentially
continuing and perfecting the process of
creation it is generally transcribed in
the Christian tradition as the word and
is closely identified with the
transcendental being of Christ as well
as with the original creative force of
God this is a very peculiar
identification from the perspective of
strip strict temporal logic because it
is the Word of God that creates order
out of chaos and that word is a
phenomenon that predates the birth of
Christ from the temporal perspective so
that's all exceptionally it's very it's
exceptionally incomprehensible I would
say fundamentally it's a an unbelievable
matrix of sophisticated ideas and one of
the reasons I started to explore this
was because you know I was very obsessed
as you all know with the dynamic
struggle between essentially between
Soviet Communism and and the Western
worldview and if you're a rationalist
and a relativist then basically what you
have to proclaim is that both societies
predicated themselves on arbitrary axiom
so arbitrary descriptions of right and
wrong and that basically what was
happening was that there was a war to
see which of those arbitrary systems
would dominate but I thought well if
it's just a matter of arbitrariness then
we're really in trouble because the only
way you could pause first of all neither
of those systems are right or better in
any real sense of the word and second
the only way that could be possibly
settled is by brute force so then I
thought well what if I look into the
origins of the ideas that are
characteristic of the West we know where
the bloody communist ideas came from
because they were written down by Marx
that's pretty obvious but the ideas of
things like natural rights and in the
West they're very peculiar ideas they're
obviously metaphysical ideas and then
you might ask yourself well are those
mere arbitrary statements or is there
something deeper underneath them and so
that's partly what led me back to the
analysis of these texts for example
because the ideas emerged out of the
text it's not like somebody just sat
around and thought the damn things up
there are very very old ideas and it
doesn't look to me like the matrix that
they emerged out of was actually a made
tricks of ideas it was more like a
matrix of behavior and it's over
thousands and thousands of years and so
that's when I started to understand that
the conception of the individual in the
West is something like that which
mediates between order and chaos and
that that's not merely uh that's an
ontological statement rather than a
theoretical statement it's a statement
about the nature of reality
not about models so to speak and you
know I would add to that the fact that
we don't understand a damn thing about
consciousness except that it clearly
exists and that it also seems to me to
be phenomenally logically accurate I
mean when you guys are you're all in
this situation right now and probably
possessed by anxiety because of it as
soon as you graduate what emerges in
front of you is a huge field of on map
potential and it seems to me that
there's no other way of saying that
that's more accurate so we could just
assume that that is what confronts you
and then what you're doing as you
navigate your way through it in one form
or another is actualizing that potential
into some into some reality that you
inhabit that is hopefully operating in
accordance with what you both need and
want but you certainly view yourself as
at least to some degree as a being that
is capable of doing that it seems to me
I mean you assume that you can choose
what you're going to do after you go to
university like you don't have infinite
choice and it seems perfectly reasonable
to presume that that's anxiety-provoking
why wouldn't it be we also know from the
empirical research that an unstructured
future is hard on people they produce
stress hormones like mad if they don't
know what they're doing or why if
there's a lot of unexpected potential
lying around
all right the fundamental story of the
first part of Genesis is predicated on
the assumption that chaos can be
conceptualized as a matrix as something
with a metaphorically female aspect a
matrix by the way that's a matrix is
something out of which matter arises
it's the same word matrix matter mother
those are all the same words and
the things that's very interesting about
the word matter is that we use it in two
ways right and I think it's a reflection
of the touhou boohoo divide one thing is
things are made out of matter and then
the other thing is that things matter
and part of the old testament
conceptualization of matter is that it's
partly matter and partly what matters
and part of the old testament
conceptually conceptualization of matter
is that the world is made out of what
matters so and i again i don't think
that's a metaphor i think your nerve I
think your nervous system is actually
set up in that manner because the way
your brain reacts to the world is as if
it matters and since your brain evolved
and since we don't know any other way of
producing an entity that can adapt to
reality without evolution then the fact
that your brain evolved to treat the
world as if it matters would indicate
that the reason for that is because it
matters and I don't see any way out of
that argument so that because the normal
argument is the physical substrate is
primary and anything that matters is
epiphenomena right that's part of the
subjective or qualia but I don't see any
evidence whatsoever that that's how your
brain is organized I think all the
evidence suggests the opposite and that
what you're first attracted to what
matters and then you parse it out into
the world so so good you try untangling
that but I haven't been able to untangle
it so
right right well you know yeah but that
is hard a girl's point is that that
meaning manifests itself that's that's
why he's a phenomenologist because the
root word of phenomenology is famous
thigh which means to shine forth and
it's the a priori state right and you
know I think that you can assimilate
those theories to ideas like the root
the ground of existence is something
like information rather than something
like matter it's actually not like
matter because what's ever at the ground
of the world we have no idea about
doesn't even act like matter
it's very strange stuff but I think it
acts at least as much like information
as it does like matter
right right well that yes that's a
reflection of the idea that limited
limitation has utility you know and so
that or that even that limitation is a
precondition for meaning or or more I
think limitation is a precondition for
being so one of the things that that led
me to conclude is that there's that
there's a there's a logic in that if
there can't be being without limitation
and limitation produces tragedy then how
is it possible to have being that's
acceptable and I think the answer to
that is well that's what the redemptive
question is the the root of morality
that the essence of morality is to
determine how to live so that you can
have being with with tragedy held in
abeyance sufficiently so that the being
is worth having it's a very tricky thing
to do because the tragedy is built into
the being and I think that what
redemptive systems attempt to manifest
portray they're a form of discovery is
how that human being could what its
structure is and part of it seems to
have to do with truth you have to
confront the thing that's tragic because
otherwise you can't deal with it that's
a big that's a huge part of it and then
you have to communicate the consequences
of that to others that's not all of it
but that's
big part of it that's the logos part of
it you know you have to embody the logos
fundamentally so okay so now I want to
move from the initial part which is the
the creation of something out of nothing
the origins of order itself I want to
concentrate on the story of Adam and Eve
and the reason I want to do that is
because I think it's an unbelievably
illuminating story in the same way that
the Mesopotamian story is illuminating
and I think it's staggering the degree
to which the information in it has been
compressed now I think what happens it's
something like this people are always
telling stories about one thing or
another and they tell stories down the
generations and I think what happens is
that as stories are handed down across
the generations all that remains of the
stories is those elements that cannot be
forgotten and so what that means is that
there's something centrally meaningful
about those elements because that's what
you remember you remember what's
meaningful you get rid of what isn't
right so if I tell you the story of what
I did today and you go off to someone
else and you retell the story you're
gonna compress it down to just a few
lines and those are the few lines that
in some sense seem to sum up the entire
story and that's the part you didn't
forget so then you might ask if if a
thousand people tell a story for a
thousand years what's left of the story
and the straightforward answer to that
seems to be well it's the part of the
story that nobody can forget and that
would be the part of the story that's
most richly meaningful now why precisely
it would be richly meaningful I think
that's a whole different question I
don't really know how to answer that I
think to some degree it echoes in people
you know it's like and we don't
understand that exactly you know when
you go to a movie and the movie will
reach a climax and all of a sudden
little it'll produce an emotional
release in you you know maybe you'll
start to cry it doesn't mean you know
exactly why it's something in you is
responding to it so it's it's it's
echoing in you in some sense so you
might even say that the structure of the
story comes to match the structure of
your caring it's something like that
so it's a mirror of your psyche and in
some way is well partly we there are
actual ways we do know that because
there are first of all what tends to
happen in the historical story is that
it isn't changed that's the rule its its
permanence so for example grizzly bears
now and grizzly bears 150 thousand years
ago they're the same and roughly
speaking the farther you go back in time
the more people are the same from one
generation to another
they don't change at all so for example
among the Australian Aborigines before
the Europeans came there's not a lot of
evidence of cultural transformation over
a twenty five thousand year period and
so I don't think we really understand
the degree to which a static culture is
actually static the same thing just
happens over and over and the same
stories are told and I don't think
they're told in exactly the same way as
the as the the the story or the game
that you're describing because first of
all the knowledge is distributed to some
degree in everyone so even if you told a
part of the story and you told it wrong
then someone else is going to correct
you so the story is actually distributed
throughout the entire society so so I
don't think it's nearly as fragile as
people assume now I don't obviously
there are times in history where those
things start to transform quite rapidly
but I think that's what happens when the
population starts to grow and diverse
separated communities start to come back
together and then the stories start to
transform but other than that I think
the the a priori condition is stability
not transformation now we do know for
example there's a group of people on in
northern Japan called the a new and God
only knows where they came from there's
all sorts of theories about that
one of the things that's interesting
about the a new is that they have a
ceremony that involves the worship of
bears that seems to have exactly the
same structure as the structures of bear
worship that have been found in
Neolithic caves in Western Europe so the
way the Bears skull is set up on the
altar and so forth is the same as the
caves that were discovered in Western
Europe even though there's a gap of
approximately twenty five thousand years
so so I don't think that broken
telephone analogy is quite right because
that's only its sentence-level first
usually and the only person who knows
the message to begin with is one person
and there's no context for the message
so it's an interesting analogy and I
also think some of its useful because I
do think stories transform themselves
across time to some degree even with the
retelling because the language is going
to shift and move and so forth but I
don't think we should assume that the
default position is noise I think we
should assume that it's signal so okay
Adam and Eve
the first thing that happens is that
they were both naked the man and his
wife and were not ashamed
so the first thing you might ask is well
what is meant by naked and what is meant
by ashamed and so then you think well
there's a number of things about people
that are quite peculiar and one is that
we're clothed and although there are
some people who go about naked it's not
the standard human position in the world
in fact you can actually trace the the
origin of cloth using the evolutionary
structure of lice because there are some
lights who have evolved to hold on to
cloth and not hair and they've tracked
the DNA development the genetic
development of those lights back more
than twenty five thousand years so
people use cloth and they use it well
they use it obviously for protection but
they also use it for all sorts of
symbolic routines but the point is is
that there it does seem to be a
particularly human relationship with the
idea of nakedness now you might ask
yourself why and what does it mean that
that the original people might have been
naked and not ashamed and why would that
be a surprise to the readers because
obviously one of the things that
sentence presumes is that the reader is
going to assume that the fact that the
men and women who were naked were not
ashamed is actually a deviation from the
norm so here's what I've made of it and
you can tell me what you think first of
all they weren't self-conscious now you
might ask well what would that have to
do with nakedness and I would say well a
huge chunk of white people don't run
around naked is because they're
self-conscious and there's a bunch of
reasons for that is that well human
beings are standing up first of all like
unlike other animals and so the most
vulnerable parts of us are exposed not
only to the world but directly to the
view of other people and so most animals
run around on all four and that means
they basically have armor
roxrite they're vulnerable parts are not
full center in front for everyone to see
so human beings also mate face-to-face
although they don't have to and that
also heightened self-consciousness and
then in relationship to shame
shame is actually a emotion that seems
to be manifested under conditions of
judgment and so you might say well
people are often afraid of public
speaking why you guys are afraid of
public spirit of public speaking okay
how many of you are completely
comfortable with public speaking oh
that's good that's quite that's quite
amazing so okay so why might people be
afraid of public speaking you bet that's
a lot of eyes looking at you right and
often people who are afraid of public
speaking won't meet the eyes they look
down and what that basically means is
they're reacting to the crowd as if it's
a predator
the best way to overcome that is to
start looking at people and you don't
look at the crowd because there isn't a
crowd you look at individuals within the
crowd and then that's no problem because
you know how to do that it's a great way
to decrease your fear of public speaking
okay so how about speaking in front of a
crowd naked that's a common nightmare by
the way so what do you think about that
sounds like fun
no why why right and so what's the
problem with the scrutiny why why that's
right you have a lot of flaws and you're
bloody well aware of them you know and
it's bad enough to have your
intellectual flaws revealed but to add
to that your physical flaws you know
when you can think about that as your
deviation from an implicit ideal it's
something like that right people don't
like that that's why you never except
for The Naked News you never see that
happening or you virtually never see
that happening except under very
specific conditions so part of the the
issue with being
naked and ashamed is that the nakedness
has to do with flaws so you might say
well what does it mean to see yourself
as naked well I think what it means is
to see yourself with all your
vulnerabilities and that's like your
local vulnerabilities which just happens
to be how hideous you are as a physical
entity but then there's even worse which
is if you're really self conscious and
aware of what it means to be vulnerable
because let's say that's what's at the
core of nakedness is you also realize
you're flawed and mortal nature across
time so that's partly the burden of the
fact that you're physically imperfect in
degenerating all at the same time and
that's something that human beings
understand and that no other animal
understands that's a big deal so I think
partly the reason that we put on clothes
is so we don't freeze to death when it's
cold but part of it also is this to
separate ourselves from continual
scrutiny a lot of that's going to be
sexual scrutiny - and evaluation we
shield ourselves from that so that we
can do some other things now and then
so the original people didn't have that
problem so I think they weren't
self-conscious that's the first thing to
notice so ok the next thing that happens
is that the atom is complaining about
the fact that he doesn't have any
company right so God does this the Lord
God caused a deep sleep to fall upon
Adam and he slept and he took one of his
ribs and closed up the flesh instead
thereof and the rib which the Lord God
had taken from man made he a woman and
brought her unto the man and Adam said
this is now bone of my bones and flesh
of my flesh she shall be called woman
because she was taken out of man so I
want to read you something about this
because one of the interpretations of
that especially feminist interpretations
of the that story is that that makes
women subordinate to men and it also
inverts the natural order because
obviously men come from women rather
than women coming from men and so the
idea there is that that's something like
a patriarchal presumption that overthrew
the original matriarchal order which
there was none of by the way that's a
faulty arc anthropological theory there
was never a pre patriarchal matriarch
it's a it's a it's a misplace myth
that's historicize because you know in
in the scheme that I showed you the
feminine is underneath the masculine so
to speak right so in some sense the
feminine nature is out of that out of
which culture Springs but that's a
psychological truth not an
anthropological truth so it is it is it
is yes and but I'm gonna read you why
that is but yes it is exactly that but
there's a reason for it
and it has to do it has to do with the
idea that the central element of human
being is logos regardless of whether
it's man or woman now logos is are also
symbolically masculine because it's
associated with the heroic part of the
individual so let me read this because
again it's too complicated for me to
conjure up on the fly so it is of course
contrary to the entire scheme of nature
that woman be derived from man and it is
very tempting to read a simple
patriarchal prejudice into that
derivation I think it is more
appropriate to give these ancient and
incomprehensible stories the benefit of
the doubt and to search for something
more profound logos is symbolically
masculine and that would be partly
because of the idea of mardik against
time at for example there are diverse
reasons for this that have little to do
with simple ideological prejudice or
with gender per se the profound implicit
idea put forth in this creation sequence
woman from man is that the individual
woman rather than the mere female is a
product of logos and not simply a
daughter of matter matter mother or
nature thus the story does not denigrate
the female as is now commonly postulated
but elevates human being itself man and
woman above it's simply material and
symbolically feminine substrate now
there's a there's a there was some there
was a whole series of ancient writings
that were uncovered in in
in the late 1950s that are now called
the Gnostic Gospels and hypothetically
their New Testament Gospels of a whole
variety of sorts that were that were
defined as non canonical by what became
the Christian Church and so they were
they all emerged in the late 1950s it's
a fascinating story because the people
who discovered them if I remember
correctly it's been a long time since I
read this their father had been killed
by someone and so they went out to find
the guy who killed him and killed him
and then they went to a cave Tiberium
and when they dug in the cave they found
all these amphora that had been buried
for thousands of years and then they
took them home and their mother used a
bunch of the papers that were inside
them to light fires with so the family
could cook but an antiquities dealer
came along and recognized them for what
they were and squirreled them away now
weirdly enough and I don't remember how
this happened either is that one of them
one of these manuscripts called the
Gospel of Thomas made its way to Karl
Yune and he was the only person in the
entire world who had access to any of
the Gnostic Gospels until probably
twenty-five years ago when they were
finally more or less released to
scholars so that's also extremely
bizarre so anyways there's a quote from
the Gospel yeah it's very very bizarre
it's a very amazing story
so anyways there's all these Gospels and
now they've been translated in various
ways and you can buy them as the Gnostic
Gospels and the Gnostics were a group of
early Christians who believed that
Redemption could be attained through
knowledge as much as Redemption could be
attained through faith and that was
basically crushed by the developing
Christian Church so anyways Young is
often regarded as a kind of Gnostic but
it's still it's really quite remarkable
that he ended up with the Gospel of
Thomas I think that's just like
incomprehensible fundamentally so a
similar idea this the individual woman
rather than the mere female is a product
of logos and so there's an idea in the
Gospel of Thomas and similar ideas put
forth in the Gospel of Thomas in more
thoroughly elaborated form Simon Peter
said to them
make merry leave us so he's talking
about the disciples and Mary Magdalene
is in amongst the disciples and so Simon
Peter says to all the disciples make
merry leave us for females do not
deserve everlasting life jesus said look
I will guide her to make her male so
that she too may become a living spirit
resembling you males for every female
who makes herself male will enter the
kingdom of heaven so the question is
what exactly does that mean
well I would say you know you can think
about it what do you think's happened
since women discovered the birth control
pill you know it seems to me
fundamentally that what's happened is
that women have taken on the attributes
of masculinity that's what they want
because that's associated with freedom
and exploration and and and the kind of
creativity that's associated with the
mind rather than I'm not going to say
mere biological creativity because it's
not mere it's important but it's not
it's not of the essence of consciousness
they say or it's not of the essence of
spirit and so I don't think that the
birth control pill could have even come
about as a possibility if there wasn't
the lingering idea in Western culture
that attributing to women the same
spiritual phenomenology that are
abilities that characterized men wasn't
the possibility right because you might
say women were emancipated because of
the pill but then you might say well
what were the preconditions that would
allow a society to do something as
radical as to invent the pill now
obviously one of the preconditions was
that there was enough of an agreement
implicit agreement among the scientific
community that the idea of allowing
women voluntary control over their own
reproductive status wasn't the kind of
heresy that should have been punished by
like instant death and even even even
though that idea was there there was
still a huge battle and still is between
Catholicism roughly speaking in the
Western world and the idea of birth
control because it's still part of
Catholic dogma that if you're a good
Catholic you don't do that and I don't
know if you
oh this or not but you know that
generally women women have a menstrual
period about once every 28 days well you
know that's built in that was built into
almost all formulations of the birth
control pill even though it wasn't
necessary so the guy who invented the
pill decided that it would be three
weeks on and one week off so that the
menstrual cycle would stay intact so
that it wouldn't look as much like a
deviation from the natural order to all
those people who are opposed to birth
control when the simple matter is is you
can take birth control all the time and
never have a menstrual period and that
isn't a problem or it's you know maybe
it has to happen now and then but it
certainly doesn't happen have to happen
on a weekly basis so Jung believed in
the 1950s he there's this phenomena that
occurred in Catholicism again which I
don't understand very well but part of
the idea that was that there was a shift
in Catholic dogma in the mid 50's and
because there was a tremendous movement
in the Catholic world to to to
appreciate Mary as a deity roughly
speaking along with Christ and and God
and the Holy Ghost so it was as if Mary
was being added as the fourth part of
the Trinity and it wasn't a movement it
wasn't an idea that the aristocracy of
the church imposed on the masses it was
exactly the other way around the idea
that Mary was to be uplifted into heaven
roughly speaking so she would be beside
God in Christ was an idea that was
really popular in the Mediterranean
countries and also in Central and South
America where where Mary worship is a
huge element of Christianity and what
happened was because of that popular
pressure the Catholic aristocracy
announced Mary's and this is where I
haven't got the terminology exactly
right her ascension into heaven in the
mid 1950s and you believe that that idea
was movement in the collective
unconscious and the movement was that
the imagination of the Western world had
progressed to the point where it was
self-evident that there was that the
feminine element of being was
underrepresented in the idea of deity
and that it needed to be elaborated up
with all of the other mostly masculine
and then he would have read that as a
precursor to the possibility that the
pill could have even become a an idea
like the underlying imagination had to
be arranged to allow that to be a
possibility before any of that research
could have even been conducted much less
the product be sold you know because you
have to you got to think how bloody much
preparation does it take for a culture
to allow a birth control device to be
sold for general use it's not like that
happens just because it's invented I
mean forget that you know it's still
people have by no means yet come to
terms with that so I'll tell you the
last the next part of this story and
then we'll stop until next week so and
the Lord God took the man and put him
into the Garden of Eden to dress it and
keep it okay so that's an interesting
idea I think because so what it's now
now what the story is proposing is that
there's a universal habitation for
mankind and the universal habitation is
the idea of the garden now Eden means
well watered place and paradise means
it's from Paradiso means a walled
enclosure so that the original garden is
a walled enclosure that's well watered
then you think well what exactly is a
garden and it seems to me that a garden
is a productive union of nature and
culture so it's another order and chaos
union right so a perfect garden is
beautiful because it's natural but it's
also beautiful because it's attended to
and paid attention to and a garden is
also something that's productive right
it's not just chaotic wilderness it's a
place where you can live so the idea is
that human beings have to live inside
walled gardens and so there's a physical
element to that which is just true and
then there's a metaphysical element to
it which is that the the environment of
a human being is the proper admixture of
chaos and order and it has to be bounded
so and then there's a there's a very
interesting corollary to that which i
think is tremendously interesting is
that there's a snake in the garden and
that's an interesting thing because part
of that is the recognition that you
can't have a place of bounded chaos in
order that's productive without having
something in it that's it's disruptive
there's no way of getting the
disruptiveness out and that's because
imagine here's the problem and this has
been discussed intensely in Christian
theology because there's a relationship
between the snake and Satan which is
something we'll talk about later but if
you if you're surrounded by infinite
potential in some sense and that's chaos
and you try to wall off part of it you
can't keep the chaos out you can only
keep it out partially in some sense
because it's gonna come sneaking back in
because you can't erect a wall that's
going to keep out all the potential from
a designated safe place and so if you
have to live in a garden you're going to
encounter snakes and there's and not
even God Himself can keep the damn
snakes out of the garden because it's a
inevitable consequence of walling off a
small section from the from the from the
Hall so let me see if I can give you an
example well I can think of a
metaphysical example which is you know
you're going to inhabit one of your
conceptual structures an attempt to keep
that matched with the world that's like
a walled space you're saying these are
the relevant things this is the place
that I can inhabit but the fact of the
matter is is that as you're walling off
that little enclosure for you to inhabit
there's dynamism all around you and the
dynamism is going to affect the
structure of this limited place that
you're attempting to inhabit and at some
point it's going to poke its head
through you just can't seal something
off from everything the thing is going
to come back in now one of the things
that happens in the Genesis story is
that the snake is actually something to
which Adam and Eve cannot not attend
that's the other thing that's so
interesting so this
snake pops up in what's essentially
paradise and human-beings attention as
he immediately drawn to it and i would
also say that's what human beings are
like you know if we walled off something
and attempted to make it perfect and
secure and something pops up inside
that's unexpected and predatory and
attractive the first thing we're going
to do is be automatically drawn to it
and then if we interact with it what
it's going to do is to increase our
consciousness and that is what happened
as human beings evolved because one of
the things we know is that we call
evolved with snakes
we co-evolved with predatory snakes and
lynn Isbell has demonstrated that the
acuity of primate vision among a very
large and diverse range of primates is
correlated quite highly with the
prevalence of predatory snakes in the
environment and so the the the the
Genesis story draws this tremendously
complicated analogy and one analogy is
snakes give people vision and the other
analogy is the snake is actually
representative of the chaos that
surrounds every bounded order and so it
tells the story of psychological
abstraction so that would be
consciousness versus the unknown and it
overlays that on primate snake and it's
because it's the same it's the same idea
at two levels of abstraction so you have
the same reaction to unexpected things
that occur in your pristine environment
as your distant ancestors would have had
to the appearance of a snake in a place
that they regarded as secure and used
the same dam circuits it's the same
thing and one of the major claims in the
story of Genesis is no gardens without
snakes and so it you know the story is
set up so that God tells us men and
women to ignore the damn snake and not
to pay any attention with it not to
interact with it and also not to eat the
fruit of the tree of the knowledge of
good and evil which we'll talk about
later but human beings don't do that
they they interact with the snake and
they become self conscious which is a
catastrophe and that's how it's shown in
the in the story as well so as soon as
human beings become self conscious and
get thrown out of paradise so you can
read it this way
we got so smart by paying attention to
the damn snakes that we figured out we
were mortal they drove cortical
evolution especially the evolution of
the visual system now I'm not trying to
reduce it to a unit dimensional
phenomena but the point is once you get
cortically elaborated enough at some
point you're going to discover time
which we have discovered and once you
discover time you're going to discover
one of your boundaries and one of your
boundaries is temporal boundary and that
means that you die and that's sort of
like the ultimate manifestation of
self-consciousness and then as soon as
you know that you're going to die while
you're not in paradise anymore that's
for sure
and then you have to start taking you
have to start preparing for the future
in a self-conscious manner and one of
the things that happens to Adam what
once God catches a master he's become
self conscious this God says to him
straightforwardly well now you've done
it you know you've become self conscious
and now we'll all your going to be able
to do for the rest of history is work
you're going to be condemned to work and
you might say well what's the definition
of work and that's easy it's the
sacrifice of the present for the future
and you won't do that unless you're self
conscious because why the hell would you
prepare for the future unless you knew
that it might consist of nothing but
trouble and you know Genesis portrays
that discovery as something that's
absolutely fundamental to the to the
ground of human existence it's only part
of what it portrays and so we'll talk
about some of the other details when we
get together next week now what I want
to do is I want to tell you this story I
want to show you how it relates to the
emergence of self-consciousness and
that's the collapse of paradox and so
it's the same idea as the descent into
the underworld so the Bible in some
sense is a descent into the underworld
and then a sentient story it's precisely
that because it's a redemptive story
history starts when people descend into
chaos and the entire historical element
of the Bible is part of the attempt of
human beings to lift themselves out of
the painful self-consciousness that
they've fallen into as a consequence of
interacting with the snake and the fruit
so